so welcome to voices with verveiki
i'm uh joined by well his colleague
we have worked together uh but uh
somebody i want to get to know more
i keep intersecting with his work and
that's
matt seagal so welcome matt
thanks john uh great to dialogue with
you
i've really enjoyed uh your work on
youtube and yes um
getting to uh be on a committee together
to supervisor a
dissertation on i guess it's that
students now doctor's work was focused
on participatory theory which is one of
the places that we
interact and intersect um
but uh yeah so i've been enjoying i
think the first time i saw you
in dialogue on youtube with someone was
um
a rebel wisdom interview between
you and ian mcgillcrist right
yeah that was wonderful i enjoyed that
thoroughly yeah
uh you know and i think uh i was just
really
um resonant i mean with both of you guys
but uh particularly
it just struck me that there are a lot
of ways that
we are concerned with the same problems
and trying to work within academia
to bridge it with
worlds contemplative spiritual types of
of worlds and practices that maybe don't
have a home yet in academia though the
doors are opening and more connections
are being made
so um yeah i'm an assistant professor at
uh
the california institute of integral
studies in a program called philosophy
cosmology and consciousness
which sounds like an amazing program i
envy you that sounds like just a
wonderful program
to be in it's a lot of fun and i teach
courses on
german idealism and process philosophy
alfred north whitehead but also other
philosophers who directly or indirectly
have sort of been
influenced by whitehead or who adopt a
broadly process
oriented view i'm teaching a course this
fall on american philosophy so
uh it's the first time i'm teaching that
subject but uh
you know that tradition pragmatism
william james
dewey um
and purse very important for me as well
but uh as an undergrad i studied
cognitive science
at university of central florida
with professors like mason cash
and sean gallagher and gallagher studied
with francisco varela
was colleagues with him and so i got
into philosophy of mind and cognitive
science but then
you know sean gallagher introduced me to
phenomenology and varela's work
and evan thompson and yeah um
the significance of phenomenology for
understanding
the mind there's a there's a what's
called a cognitivist paradigm
um and a computationalist paradigm that
looks at the mind in one way and then
that's what i was you know the cognitive
science department at ucf was mainly
focused there but sean gallagher was
bringing this other phenomenological
direction
right i was very interested in that and
started reading who cyril and marilu
ponti and varela's work and
evan thompson's work and learning about
the inactive perspective
which um i think can easily be
i think it's it's helpful when we're
doing
cognitive science and epistemology and
when we're trying to understand the
biological basis of mind
but what interested me about an activism
um
was how does it deal with ontological
and cosmological questions
right right and there's not much really
within the inactivist paradigm about
those questions
um it's more like they're bracketed
which is a typical phenomenological move
and so i got interested more in
whitehead because i was like oh
here's the cosmology and the ontology
maybe that
makes synthetic places at the inactivist
paradigm and autopoetic
biology in a grounded it grounds it onto
logically
it's like process ontology provides for
um the missing ontology in an activism
and i've been talking to evan thompson
about this for a while and
he's slowly but surely i think
moving towards a more white hedian
perspective oh it'd be great if the
three of us
spoke i mean evan's a colleague and
friend of mine and it would be great for
the three of us
uh to speak together sometime we should
probably try and set that up that sounds
like a really interesting
triangle for discussion i would love
that yeah
um but so you know whitehead was has
been really influential for me but also
um jorge ferreira is a colleague of mine
right
i would like to meet him by the way
that's another uh trial log we could do
yes that sounds fantastic um he's in
spain right now
because cis has been virtualized he
teach he
he teaches online anyway so but uh yeah
his participatory theory
and participatory study or approach to
religion and spirituality uh allowed me
to see how
there's a different way of getting at
the science religion or science
spirituality
um culture war that that doesn't require
that
a they be at war or even b that they're
sort of like
non-overlapping magisteria or whatever
but that actually
at a deeper level there's this
participatory
way of knowing that is essential for
science
and also for for religion yes and
we get into more dogmatic forms of
either materialism or
some kind of creationism or
fundamentalism when we stop
consciously um when we're when we when
we lose conscious awareness of that
participatory dimension of our knowledge
yeah yeah so these that's sort of the uh
my influence is where i'm coming from
and um
clearly you know we have a lot of
overlaps and i guess
you know i uh what i would love to talk
to you about and whatever else you want
to talk about it's
great too is um
what you think about these the the the
cosmological
and ontological questions and
metaphysical questions
that uh from an activist or
participatory perspective
um do we need to say more say as an
activist do we need to say more about
the cosmological
backdrop or context of um
of this approach that's very good i was
just talking to jordan hall about this
we were talking about um you know
a reinventio i i've taken this term from
kerry who did a
really wonderful book on augustine's
invention of the inner cell
but he said the word he wanted to use
with the latin word inventio which means
both to discover and to make
it stands on that and so we were talking
about sort of the reinvention of
rationality
and how once we once we move it out of
the computational algorithmic cartesian
paradigm
it starts to move into uh something that
starts to overlap with virtue ethics and
with a sense of reverence and um et
cetera
and but this this general question uh
uh also came up because he made the
point that there is
there's a code there's a co-definition
between that
model of rationality and a model of the
world as fundamentally lacking
um in creativity and he he made the
criticism he said
you know the ontology admits this moment
of absolute creativity at the beginning
and then no
no no you know no ontological creativity
for for the rest right and we talked
about how whitehead sort of bounced off
of that
that project because you know ultimately
the failure right uh uh
for godelian reasons the failure of that
whole project and then he turns
to a metaphysics as you know in which
you know
creativity goes it's not it's not you
have to hear that well you know i'm
speaking to the
people watching it's a much more
ontological notion than we usually use
that word
people hear creativity and think it's
something like a psychological capacity
yeah exactly right yeah whitehead meant
it metaphysically and it's not
it's impersonal creativity it's not the
creativity of
of a genius like no not that
so and i want to explore that with you
um
uh because i have an abiding interest in
whitehead um
and i've read a lot of the books i have
to confess like
i could not get through process in
reality it was very
and i've read some pretty tough nuts but
that that's a very hard book but i've
read a lot of the you know
religion in the making and a lot of his
other work
so um and you mentioned the religion in
the making in the video i watched
but the the thing that get back to
jordan's point and to answer your
question is
he said but if you shift into
um an ontology in which there is genuine
novelty in some sense and there's
genuine complexification
in some sense then he says then
correspondingly that model
of rationality also has to be given up
and we were talking about how the two
things they have to sort of be given up
in tandem they have to be given up in
concert like you have to reinvent your
both
if you'll allow me these really
contested words there's a reinventing of
both reality and rationality
and they have to be reinvented together
if you
right and so i think the question you
posed to me is directly pertinent the
question is
does in so far and i would argue that i
would argue this
that insofar as 4e cognitive science
i think explicitly in in right
undermines
the cartesian conception of cognition
that of course
strongly entails that it undermines the
cartesian conception of rationality
and then correspondingly it is obligated
to reinvent here the conception of
reality
so because i those two have to be
reconfigured
in a coordinated fashion so i think your
question is directly pertinent and
relevant
i think i think there's some i i don't
want i want to make it sound like a
moral obligation
but there's at least an epistemic
obligation on people
in four e cog side i sometimes stick
into 50
but because i i think the notion of
exactation are really important but
whatever for e cog sir i think there is
an epistemic obligation on them uh to
get
into the ontology and there's also
historical precedent
i mean so dreyfus is one of the
godfather figures
of four e cognizant and he comes out of
the heideggerian tradition
explicitly directly repeatedly and of
course hattier's project
is the project of extending
phenomenology into fundamental ontology
and so i for both historical reasons
and epistemic reasons i think your
question is directly
directly pertinent and it is a bit of
you know it's a bit of i don't want to
call it a question a concern
why more people haven't taken that up uh
and so i'd be very happy for the reasons
i've just
reviewed to talk to you about this i
think i think that question is
very strongly motivated
yeah um that's wonderful i love what
you're saying
and framing this in terms of uh
reinventing
the relationship between reality and
reason or how we conceive of these two
and yes exactly that uh the
4ea or inactive just short
critique of cartesian rationality and
the cartesian conception of mind
strongly implies that the cartesian
conception of matter
that's based on that conception of mind
also has to go exactly
exactly and once you do that um
you know there are places in if so
varela
wrote a paper i think it was the last
one he published with andres weber um
life after kant oh it happened right
there i haven't read that
oh it's it's it's a i think it's a
crucial paper he
begins by by uh quoting whitehead at the
beginning
um something about a conflict of
doctrines is an opportunity
and uh and he goes on to use some
whitehead language about the subject
poll
that emerges in the context of an
autopoetic
uh organism um subject poll being
drawn from whitehead's process ontology
um and and varela ends up arguing that
um our conception
of at least living matter and
again the paper is titled life after
kant so he's engaging with
kant's critique of judgment and
the study of uh teleology in
self-organ what kant uses the term
self-organizing
beings and varela ends up saying
look this type of self-organization
associated with life cannot be
understood mechanistically
and it is purposeful it's a form of
imminent teleology and kant is also
making all these distinctions already
um in 1790 but varela is going back to
kant and saying look he was right we
can't understand this mechanistically
and he's he just hints that we probably
need a new ontology
uh a new understanding of what nature is
in order to make sense of this
in his you know merely ponte was saying
this too in the in the 60s right before
he died
drawing on whitehead drawing on bergson
drawing on
shelling and so we need a new conception
of matter
and physics already kind of gave it to
us they call it energy
but but energy if we just let
physics tell us about energy it's it's
mathematical equations and it's like
what is what are these what's the
content of these equations right
right because it's otherwise it's a very
strange
it's the strange idealism of
contemporary physics where it's like
ultimately it all rests on these
mathematical equations
formulas yeah and the white hat's point
is like what did these form what is the
content of them and so
he says you know energy vectors are um
he calls them feeling vectors and
there's a
primitive form of he calls it prehension
yep
it goes on even at the quantum level
um and that he thinks that new
conception of what matter is or what
energy is allows us to understand
the emergence of everything else that
came in the course of evolution
including
stars and galaxies including
living cells multicellular plants
complex animals language using mammals
it makes sense in the context of a
pan-experiential
cosmology that whitehead articulates
whereas
the old material that descartes defined
even though
modern science got rid of his
disembodied soul
it kept the extended matter in motion
you can't explain the emergence of
consciousness i would argue
if you if you keep that old ontology of
matter
and the whole inactive paradigm and
phenomenology and heidegger and
marily ponti seems to be um
there was heidegger was less inclined to
engage with the sciences
but merely ponti was more inclined and
obviously the inactivists are more
inclined to engage with neuroscience
and but there's this bracketing when it
gets to these ontological questions
that for me doesn't go far enough
there's there's
there's an unwillingness to make
positive statements about nature
that nature is as whitehead says um
that nature has value and
interiority to some degree yeah all the
way down because that's
uh i mean obviously materialists dismiss
that but i think a lot of
you know in conversation with evan for
him that's too much of a speculative
claim
yes yes but i'm saying in order to have
a coherent cosmology
cosmology is not a positive science you
know we have lots of measurements that
the ancients didn't have
but uh it's gonna be speculative
because you know um
we can't step outside of it you know
we're in it we're in the midst of it so
we're always you know i would i would
say cosmology is always endocosmology
you know like we're within the thing we
are
an expression of the very order that
we're trying to understand you know this
gets back to the
reason reality entanglement that you
were talking about right
that's very good nora bateson has a term
for that she calls it warm data
that we're always enmeshed in the warm
data uh and that
she argues that we need and this is what
i agree with here
we need a more dialogical notion of
reasoning and rationality which is also
by the way emerging in cognitive science
the work of my friend greg enriquez and
the work of mercier and sperber and
others and all this
increasing work that we actually even
argumentatively we reason better
in distributed cognition rather than a
monological uh cognition so
that's something that feels sort of
white heading to me
um but let let's let's let's i mean
i would want to anyway because i i have
so much respect and affection for evan
um let's give him his view
in the sense of let's say for many
people
he he and you know and evan is not some
hand-fisted physical list or anything
like that
right so sensitive reflective deeply
insightful thoughtful guy
so he represents you know at least a
prima facie response
to the white hitting move i'm not gonna
say we're gonna end up there
but but can i suggest one thing because
there is there was there's one group of
thinkers that i think
do do the ontological move um
and so the pivotal figure for that
and she's not given enough credit i
think is i don't know if you've read
alicia guerrero's work
in my actions i'm familiar with it but i
haven't read it yet no
yeah and so i mean she starts from the
same point you just started from when
the varela
webber is i think it's weber because
he's german but ah okay varela and
uh weber okay uh namely kant and the the
problem of you know
uh the the tree and the self-organizing
of the organism and what euro argues
is that we have to actually make an
ontological revision
and there and there are two kind of
significant ones she proposes
and the reason why i'm putting this up
is that i see evan
sort of committed to at least something
like this and that might give us a way
of building some common ground so that's
a suggestion i have
and so um you know gerardo talks about
and you know and this is and this is and
this isn't just ontology because she
points out it's being
presupposed when we try and explain
action
including cognitive action she makes a
distinction
between causes and constraints and she
introduces this notion of constraint as
something already being used but not
explicated within existing science and
then she argues that it can be
fruitfully re-understood as a bringing
back into ontology
of aristotle's notion of formal cause
right um yeah but then she did
i just want to say briefly what's funny
is i haven't read her book but i've read
terrence deacon's book and he was
accused
accused of kind of lifting some ideas
without yeah with with
evidence i've seen some of the slides
yeah so i'm familiar with your terms
that you're describing because
i've read his book yeah um
i don't know what to know about to do
about deacon i mean
yeah i mean when she sent out that email
where he said i you know i've never met
you
and she's got him and her talking and
the slide from her presentation is
behind
the two of them and it's got some of
this terminology on it it's like
wow so yeah uh but that's
you know let's let's put aside academic
gossip that's why
i focus on on guerrero because i think
he
overwhelmingly has precedence um so
and the the difference is also
she she does something that's a little
bit
although she's invokes aristotle's
formal cause she also seems to be
challenging
now this is something i'm we're drawing
from her then it couldn't give you like
a sentence that explicitly says this but
this is
the notion of real possibility
which against right and the the
uh and and this is this is something we
might want to talk about with respect to
whitehead because this is an
area where i'm sort of you know
wrestling with whitehead a bit
but uraro argues that uh the west has
privilege
has privileged actuality over
possibility
and has rendered actuality as virtually
synonymous
with reality um and then this is very
problematic
uh because the the science the practice
of the science
actually presupposes real possibility
one
clear example you know conservation of
energy
uh requires that potential energy is a
real thing
right because the conservation that's
the only way you can preserve the con
it can't be that it's only an abstract
thing it has to be a real thing
or else the conservation is not really
happening etc and so you have those
kinds of arguments
and so for to my mind whether or not
she's right
that's another thing but what i see here
doing is i see her trying to
argue from science and from cognitive
science
from especially from an active cognitive
science dynamical systems cognitive
science
for a fundamental revision uh to
you know some of the core building
blocks of the ontology bringing back
because
the cartesian notion of matter is bound
up with the reduction of all the causes
to efficient causation right and then
that's what destroys human morphism too
right
and the formal causation and
of course descartes from the whole uh
traditional he he gives uh priority
to uh to actuality i think to the point
of equating
uh realness with actuality and all the
in the background here i know herrera
and a lot of complexity theorists don't
go there but in the background here
at least for descartes was a theological
issue yes yes
he didn't you know his model of nature
has extended mechanism
he was he was kind of saying look i
don't know how god does it
that'd be blasphemous for me to claim to
know how god does it but we can use the
mathematics that god gave us
to describe it this way you know and
as science advanced from that point
forward they took his analytical tools
and left the theological move behind
and and equated the modeling with the
way nature actually is
descartes wasn't saying that's how it
actually is he was still and i think
had a foot in the um the ancient
tradition of saving the appearances
but the door to a reduction of
the human mathematical model to the way
that
the ontology of the physical world
actually is
um because that's the direction later
scientists went
just getting rid of the idea that um
that actually god and the human
nature and the human mind are both
for descartes they're expressions of god
i mean there's one infinite substance
spinoza was a little clearer on this
point i think
so but um anyways there's a theological
issue behind the scenes here
that gets left out of the conversation
in
modern science um and i get why
but it's also important when we do start
to reimagine or reinvent
the relationship between reason and
reality that we don't
we don't we don't pretend like it's a
purely secular
sort of oh i agree i think that's
profoundly right
i think i mean i think um
i mean i think the one of the things i
was talking with jordan about is the
idea that
you know the notion when you when you
moved and here's where the pragmatists i
think are helpful
when you move to a view of reality not
as
um as fundamentally unchanging but as
having some genuine novelty creativity
whatever word we want to put on it
in its in its fundamental ontology and i
think there are good arguments for
making that move by the way
then your notion of uh of rationality is
going to be
right not one of trying to not not not
the algorithmic machine that fire
finds the final fixed picture it's going
to be like what's emphasizing james it's
going to be
right a reliable adductivity to a
environment
that is in a fundamental sense changing
and then if that's the case then i would
argue two things come out of that
give me a second because i'm going to
return to your point
um two things are going to come out of
that right you're going to you're going
to
you're going to put a premium on
reliable abilities to
overcome self-deception and reliable
abilities to enter into right
relationship uh
with that environment and so i think
you're starting to now get into the
realm
of virtue properly understood and then a
virtue that is going to i would argue is
going to be central to that
and here i'm making use of woodruff's
idea it is the virtue of reverence
because reverence is like it's on the
it's
it cognitively right it has to do with
awe and wonder and insight
and as a cognitive scientist you know
and it's a psychologist the insight
machinery is the same machinery by which
you
realize your own self-deception because
that's what really a moment of insight
is
you're right you realize that you've
mis-framed things but
uh ah is also a
um is an experience of humiliation
not in our current senses of the word
but in the older sense of the word
the sense that you right you uh
have to undergo transformation you have
to accommodate yourself
you have to conform yourself to a
reality that is demanding on you because
it exceeds
your grasp in some sense that's what the
experience of awe is
um at least psychologically speaking and
i think of reverence as
that virtue that plugs us into
awe in the right way so that we are
always
um we're reliably virtu
we're reliably open to um
dealing with self-deception and reliably
open to
reconforming to a reality that
continually
continues to transcend us and so
the odd thing here and see this is very
odd is
that the notion of rationality as sort
of this aspirational adaptivity
carries with it a commitment to the
cultivation of the virtue of reverence
but then i put it to jordan i said
but reverence requires a metaphysics
right that we'll call it fourth you
can't just if you're in if you're
and so the standard world view is not
one for which people properly
can experience reverence they'll have
frank they'll have fragmented moments
here and there right and so i think
if if you'll allow me to stretch the
word theology
i i i'm giving an argument for why i
think there's
the if if what we're talking about is a
mutual reconceptualization
reconfiguration
redesign of rationality
and reality then that in our ontology
which can evoke reverence
is actually central to
that reconfiguration in a proper fashion
so i don't think you can leave
the theological out of this
reconfiguration
for that reason what do you think what
do you think of that
i mean i think it's great i think it's
um very similar to the argument
whitehead makes
in the beginning of science in the
modern world about how
european science emerges out of a
particular theological context in which
the human being let's say like descartes
has faith in his own
reason that it is capable of knowing
the world in some important sense um
and that without that faith in the
rationality of nature
science can never get off the ground and
that faith itself
we can't prove in advance that nature is
intelligible yeah
yeah we have to us we have to assume it
and then engage as if it were true in
order to have it confirmed in what we
discover right um and
that's faith you know now we have
scientific positions i mean they're i
would say they're philosophical
positions but like
eliminative materialism yeah um
where it's as if the possibility
of scientific knowledge isn't really
something that's questioned it's just we
have scientific knowledge and this is
what it reveals to us that
yes there's just a bunch of matter in
motion and our brain is just a
complicated
piece of material and we have a word
like consciousness that
really just indicates a series of
behaviors that we follow from
its utterance or whatever and i think
that ends you know
when you lose the the ground of
reverence and i'm not you know i'm sure
paul and patricia churchlin have
reverence you know they're they're
searching for an
ethical ground in the context of
eliminative
metaphysics and so they're aware of
the issue and they want to i'm you know
they're i'm sure they're virtuous people
but
i i'm not disputing anybody's character
i'm talking about i mean
i'm talking about the metaphysical
framework yeah go ahead exactly likewise
but um i think the framework has
implications
and that you know when we adopt
a view of the physical universe that
says it's a deterministic mechanism
even if we don't direct you know like
someone like richard dawkins doesn't
make direct
claims i mean he he still thinks human
beings are free we can rebel against our
selfish genes and
have morality and have law
and have politics but metaphysically
it's not clear how that's possible
whitehead calls this the bifurcation of
nature
yes yes and i think that that view of
what the universe is
has it has psychological implications
and sociological implications and
they're not good
yes um yeah go ahead on that i
i i mean i like that um i like like
i think that line of argument makes
sense to me
um so and i mean
and there is a move within epistemology
even to bring in you know there's
there's
virtue epistemology right that and uh
when we're talking about knowledge we're
we're talking more about a virtuous
process that puts us into a reliable
right relationship
rather than uh you know some sort of you
know
algorithmic method or something like
that or
or something in which we've got you know
certainty about our propositional claims
uh again it's it's very pragmatic in
that sense
so but is there
i mean
if if if like so this is one of the
things that
intrigues me about neoplatonism and why
i keep returning to it
and i know that white has white head has
a long
a deep association with the platonic
tradition um
yeah so is you know because
i won't repeat this argument but i've
got arguments out there that
i i think one of the central functions
maybe the central function of cognition
at least of our general intelligence is
a capacity i call relevance realization
and how it's
deeper than the propositional and i
think uh the metaphysical pull i think
relevance realization is an affordance
relationship it's between
the organism and the environment but if
you'll allow me the metaphysical pull
the metaphysical correspondent although
i'm not offering a correspondence theory
of truth right to
relevance realization is intelligibility
and the neoplatonus
they sort of they take you know falling
from promenities they take
intelligibility as the thing they're
going to build their ontology from
right rather than presupposing it and
building an ontology
they do what you just suggested a moment
ago they asked the question of
how is science possible and how does
reality have to be
and we keep you and i are dancing around
this question right
and so what what occurs to me though is
you know given what we just said
one of the things that we're introducing
is kind of it was we're introducing
something like a dynamic
intelligibility unlike the neoplatonic
static right
i mean there's the emanation and the uh
and the return but you know what i mean
it's right that being is
ultimately static now i think yeah go
ahead
well i'm just going to turn it as a
question to you
um one way i've tried and that might be
a misunderstanding one way i've tried to
understand
whitehead is to try
and get an ontology that accounts for
a dynamic intelligibility and an
intelligibility
right i'm using it the way he uses it
right that something
because you know an ontology that allows
me to explain
my experience of the work of art and my
understanding of the scientific theory
i'm talking about
intelligibility broadly construed that's
why i pointed it to you know
the fundamental ability of relevance
realization to make sense
like you know like evan's sense-making
idea
uh it's it's in that family is that a
is that a fair take on it
yeah i think so i think so i think
reading whitehead as a neoplatonist
is um an essential interpretive
uh approach to even being able to grasp
what he's
trying to say um good good good and but
he's not an emanationist
no no yeah i mean oh this is interesting
a thing that came up in our
the dissertation defense that we were
part of was the
you brought it up the uh emanationist
versus emergent
yeah and that i think i think we were
all in
somewhat agreement that there's a kind
of um both and going on here
yes i i that's why i'm deeply influenced
by eredina
because the emergence and the emanation
and and the model and the theology they
are completely
inter-penetrating and into reporting
sorry i interrupted you but go
please go that's fine that's fine uh
what i see whitehead doing is
um you know the the platinus's
emanationist scheme from you know the
one through the levels down to matter
yeah uh
on some readings and i think a close
reading of the ned's shows that
platinus already had a sense of this but
it's not as though
this is a dualism between matter and the
one no
no um matter strictly speaking doesn't
exist
but but it's there as a pull and what
whitehead allows us to see more clearly
and again it's not like this is
necessarily in conflict with platinus
it's just
no no please but but whitehead would say
i kind of drew it here as you were as
you were talking you know i don't know
if you can see this
oh no it's a green screen
i think it's important enough to see the
graphic i'm just going to turn off my
background for a second
so um it's
the the yeah the skate where
you know the one emanates into matter
but matter is itself
also um possessed of potential
yeah yeah and and evolves back towards
the one
or or you know emerges back towards the
one um
or evolves through a series of emergent
you know yeah
the world's soul intellect and so on
back to the one and what whitehead is
saying is that these two poles
are he he tries to integrate them in a
conception of
creativity which is for him it's the
universal of universals it's the
ultimate category of his scheme
right even more ultimate than god god's
a creature of creativity
right um and so i think uh
we can we can read whitehead as a
neoplatonist
as long as we're clear that he's not an
emanationist as platypus
and he's also dynamic right and then
because of the because the creativity
now that's where he's more like arigina
or right yeah because there are units
first so that's a great way of putting
it
because aerogena sees creation
as the category that supersedes
or and also grounds both emanation
and emergence or emanation and return um
there's a deep similarity there
yeah i think there's um a sort of
a heterodox lineage that runs through
western thought yeah um irgina would be
part of it the the
you know like amblicus and proplus and
you know
yeah agrippa and then the whole like
occult tradition
through the renaissance and um you know
descartes was searching for
the rosicrucians and trying to like yeah
add some dream i mean
descartes and newton all those guys way
weirder than
well then we think they're yes very much
scientific origin story makes it seem
yeah but like you know if you look at
kepler uh he was a galileo
too they were astrologers newton's an
alchemist
i don't want to get into the occult
necessarily but i think
there's a way in which um there's a
heterodox lineage through western
thought that tends to be
uh participatory it tends to be um
pan psychist in some way or another yes
um you know in the modern period it's
like
you know bruno giordano bruno is part of
this tradition leibniz is part of this
uh shelling i think yes um
and whitehead's i think in that lineage
right
yes it's it's a rendering that avoids
some of the
typical thought mistakes i think that
the western
philosophical tradition tends to get
criticized for like
uh dualism or uh this sense of
disembodied rationality
or whatever um we can't
you know western philosophy is complex
right and there's i'm just pointing out
that there's this other tradition that's
um in some ways still ahead of us
or that we're inheriting it and you know
but not that the cognitive sciences
aren't aren't advancing this
um domain of inquiry in a in a in an
exciting way
i think they haven't been done before
yeah but i think you're right that
there's more
i'm trying to draw out uh connections
uh because the okay so first of all
thank you for the agreement
uh because then that affords me making a
move which is
you know tapping into the work of our
arthur versus lewis who you know
he argues that you know the neoplatonic
tradition is the spiritual cognitive
grammar of the west
i love that yeah yeah and
and so if if the figure
of whitehead is somebody whose
philosophy
um is giving us a dynamic neoplatonism
one that will allow us to reconfigure
uh reinvention uh you know
real reality and reason in a coordinated
fashion
it also would afford a way of
reinventing and recovering
that spiritual tradition that has been
running
through the or the heterodox that you've
just mentioned
um that the you know a dynamic
neoplatonism
could be a way of reinventing the
cognitive cultural grammar
cultural cognitive grammar of
spirituality that's been running through
the west
is that because i heard something like
that i wanted to make sure i wasn't
misreading or reading into you
i heard that something like that coming
out of the video
that you did uh for the future faces of
spirit
i heard something like that is that is
that fair
is that is that definitely because yes
definitely
there's a neoplatonist uh i mean i'm
my blog is called footnotes to plato you
know right right
drawing from whitehead and that's
definitely where i situate myself but
there's a
there's another typical reading
misreading of plato i would say that
imagines him as like
a duelist and he's got this ideal world
up there and then just
the world of appearances down here and
it's like
i don't think that you can read a
dialogue like the symposium
and end up believing that white that
plato is some kind of a duelist
yeah i agree with that so there's we
need to read plato more carefully
and i think whitehead and to some extent
is preserving the notion of platonic
forms or he calls them eternal objects
which alongside actual occasions are the
two most like
important uh categories in his scheme
and
one way of thinking of them is eternal
objects are potentials and
actual occasions are actualities right
and concrescence is the growing together
of both of these two poles of reality
right whitehead's use of the notion of
platonic forms is almost
inverted in the sense that whereas you
do get the sense in plato
that the forms have some kind of
preeminence reality
he's leaning more in the emanationist
direction in that sense whereas
whitehead is saying
the forms are he says deficient
in actuality and that he has
an ontological principle which for him
says that outside of actual occasions
there's nothing the only reason for
anything is going to be an actual
occasion
and that eternal objects he says ingress
into actual occasions but the agency is
with the actual occasions
right not the forms that have preeminent
reality and
that the world of experience is some
pale imitation or copy
the forms don't actually exist until
they ingress
in the context of an occasion of
experience but they're
they're real without existing or being
actual
they're eternal which their eternal
their potentials
and so whitehead does bring back in this
notion of a formal
causality right right um but as
a as a as a source of possibility that's
not yet
actualized um and
this again is a there's a theological
background here the
western tradition tends to imagine god
as pure act
right pure activity no passivity
no no no no potential in god
and whitehead's like well god has both
poles yeah because i mean
so i'm very also deeply influenced by
the kyoto school
and you know nishitani and religion and
nothingness and one initiative's
critique was
the west's reduction of realness
to actuality has really
hamstrung its ability to respond to the
problem of nihilism
because there can be no positive reading
to emptiness
right whereas the east has right you
know the daltech is the space inside the
cup
that makes the cup useful and you know
those kinds of metaphors
where and he argues that you know uh
potentiality um is is actually given
also a problematic i would say
preeminence um in the eastern traditions
and it strikes me that if we could
somehow
get it right you know about the
relationship
uh between them if we had a notion of
realness
especially of dynamic intelligibility
and real novelty
that somehow could integrate give equal
prominence
preeminence or equality again i guess uh
um equal reverence maybe is one of the
word i wanted
to actuality as a ground of realness
and to possibility as a ground of
realness i
i think that would that would go a long
way because
i think i mean i think religion and
nothingness is one of the great books
i i think his argument about um the fact
that that nietzsche was ultimately
bound into a metaphysics that equated
actuality
with realness that he couldn't he
couldn't go through the greatest
he couldn't go through the greatest not
of all the doubt that flips
and allows you to see the emptiness is
actually
the ground of possibility as what is
most real
what do you think about that as a
proposal
again nishitani is a philosopher i've
i've only read
um about that there's a philosopher
named um jason wirth that writes a lot
on shelling
yeah uh and he writes some books he has
a book where he compares nishitani and
shelling so i know nishtani in that
context and
i agree i love what you're saying about
how the west responds to nothing and it
doesn't really have a positive
deal for it to play or to emptiness and
uh
i think um that that's crucial
and um
i wanted to go somewhere else with that
but it i've lost it um
well take a moment matt there's no rush
yeah
i don't know that fire is coming um
yeah well nietzsche you you know i've
written a little bit comparing him
at least his late um writings
on will to power and he starts to
articulate uh
and he may have been losing his mind at
this point but he starts to articulate
an ontology that's based on um power and
perspective it's some sometimes called
perspectivism
that's very similar to whiteheads in
some ways
uh where he um nisha says something like
look it's not that there's no meaning
it's that there's too much meaning in
effect
in other words there's too many
perspectives vying for one another to
dominate
and win out as the perspective that
that's truly meaningful so he's like
his nihilism there is like not it's not
that there's nothing it's that we need a
um
we we've lost an orientation amidst the
plurality of meaning
that can guide us towards more valuable
and virtuous modes of existence i guess
uh and because the old religious
setup was was collapsing as capitalism
and secularism
rolled in and you know nietzsche lost
his mind
i think as a result of of losing that
orientation
recognizing nihilism but again it's like
his last semi-coherent writing is
pointing out that it's not that there's
no meaning it's that there's too much
yeah uh so that's interesting
because that's kind of like the issue of
about combinatorial explosion of the
available
information yeah um and i i think
there's something deeply right about
that um
so the idea of emptiness
is i think reconciliable with that
because the idea of emptiness
is also like it's intertwined with
the note the notion of the
interpenetration of everything
with everything else right it's um
but the idea i'm just wondering if
there's a way of bringing
bringing back nishitani's critique of
saying
yeah but what would be needed right
wouldn't be just like the solution to
nietzsche's problem of too many
perspective
isn't one perspective dominating all the
perspectives it has to be something
that's transparent
if you'll allow me to neologism here
it's trans perspectival
and therefore gives a ground in terms of
which perspectives can be judged and
evaluated
right and then that's still where i
think nietzsche
you know if you stare too long into the
abyss it begins to stare back into you
i think that's still where there's an
abysmal element
in nature because he couldn't ask the
question of
what is the ground from which the
perspectives emerge this takes us back
to this point we were before of asking
what is it about reality that makes a
multiplicity of perspectives
makes this kind of complex and
and innovative intelligibility
possible for us yeah well so it almost
seems like
um the the modern mine and
the post-modern mind nietzsche let's say
as an exemplar
is in a sense suffering as a result of
the loss
of this transcendent
source of orientation like god as a
parent yeah yeah
who's going to make sure it's all you
know god designed this whole thing if
you're good it's going to be okay
right right we lost that yes and the
initial response to that could be like
anger almost yes and you you get this in
the sort of reactionary
atheism that it's kind of died down more
recently but several years you know
there's the whole
four horsemen of the apocalypse and
hitchens and dawkins and those guys but
there's an anger that that god doesn't
exist anymore and it's there's an anger
at the people that still believe in it
because
it's like it's almost like unfair that
we don't have that but
i think the move to get beyond this
nihilism
of being angry that we don't have a god
the father
to like make sure it's all going to be
okay the move is
is to see an emptiness a source of
creativity and see
that it's not that we can't relate to
something like god anymore
it's that we're responsible for enacting
that dimension of reality yeah well put
well right
we're involved in it and if we don't
it's like you know anthropologists will
point out that many
um primal peoples will
view ritual as uh sort of symbolic i
mean they don't view it as symbolic
enactment themselves that's the
anthropological view from the outside
but that that they feel like if they
stopped performing the ritual the
universe would fall to pieces
yeah yeah yeah you know and for a modern
person
yeah yeah participant well the modern
person would be like well that's
it's obviously not gonna fall apart if
you don't pray to this you know the
sun's gonna keep rising even if you
don't
you know bow to it in reverence every
morning and yet
there's a there's a deeper way in which
we lose touch with
the meaning of the sunrise if we're not
uh
reverential as we as we take in that
spectacle
yeah something does collapse
yeah the conduit that connects our
consciousness to its cosmic ground
gets severed yes and so yeah we need to
take responsibility for
god making you know yeah
i don't mean that in a purely socially
constructivist sense or anything
i mean it like we have a biological
instinct
for god making that is what allows us to
form societies and complex civilizations
and we've lost that and so yeah the
thing's collapsing and this has happened
before it's not
new but theology is important and
religion is important
it's just they're different metaphysical
context within which
to interpret what it is and if we've
lost the old
notion of a transcendent god it doesn't
mean there's not some
function that god can play and whitehead
i just want to share a quote from
whitehead and then i'll want to hear
what you think about this but
whitehead says in process and reality
and i don't know if you got this far but
he says uh
one of the most important functions for
philosophy in the modern world
is to secularize the function of god
yeah in our ontology
um and i think a lot of
my work is rooted in that
call that white had made yeah he
attempted to do it and i don't think his
process theology is ultimately
fully um
coherent even but it's at least uh it's
at least a sketch of the direction we
need to move in to like hold
opposites and polar tension and
recognize the potentiality in god and
not just the actuality yeah
so yeah that that's i think that's
beautiful
i i really like how you
put that so i wanted i i
i wonder then so i mentioned earlier on
that i i sometimes want to add a
fifth e because it and this i predict
it's going to come into more prominence
in cognitive science especially because
of the i think groundbreaking work being
done by michael anderson
and beyond uh uh phonology and and the
hen and others
and the circuit reuse hypothesis and and
this is the idea that the brain is a
sort of an uh an exacting machine um
that what it does is it can take
circuitry that evolved for one function
and then
exact it right because every every
entity has not only its intended effects
it has side effects and it's possible to
find the configuration of the side
effects that are also functional
in another environment and so evolution
typically doesn't work
uh from scratch and then if you if you
adopt a model which i argue if you are
at length other
elsewhere that you need to see cognition
as you know
something deeply analogous uh to
evolution in which it's
dynamically introducing variation and
then putting selective pressure on it
etc
then it makes sense to think about a
cognitive version of
acceptation a biological
cultural example is my tongue right it
evolved for
poison detection and mastication but
it's been accepted for speech
most organisms who have tongues don't
have speech
or right but it's been accepted yeah so
is it possible that so this is this is
wildly speculative
but we're we're we're playing in an
adventure of ideas right and whitehead
talks about that airplane has to take
flight but it has to be able to land
again so hopefully
well i'm very comfortable in my armchair
so let's go
i'm wondering if because you talked
about that yet we have let's
you know it's the augustine notion right
that we have this sort of god function
and i i agree with you i take that very
seriously and i'm wondering if one of
the jobs
of the reworking in our ontology the
code you know the reader the reinvention
of reason and rationality is to afford
an exactation of that function in a way
that now fits
the context that we are in that that's
part of
what that ontology should be doing
because
part of the meaning crisis another way
of understanding the meeting crisis
is that function is hungry within us and
it can't find
a place to operate and what the
demographics show like with the rise of
the nuns is
these people aren't sort of dawkins uh
you know atheists
no no no that hunger is expressing
itself in all kinds of auto didactic
fragmentary often weird metaphysics
and and you know uh you know
small scale narcissistically based
religions
uh you know the religion of me and
things like that
of which i'm quite critical uh
so i don't think that function can go
unaddressed
uh but as you've indicated i think uh
you know
we can't simply return um because you
you know you mentioned like
literalisms and fundamentalisms are also
um
a problematic and profound way yeah
so could it be that one of the functions
that
that this one one of the design features
that one of the things we demand from
this ontology in order to
you know pragmatically evaluate it as
good
is that it can afford an exactation of
that god function so
it it is now adaptively engaged again
once again for individuals and for
collections of individuals
what do you what do you think of that as
a proposal yeah i love that
um you know i my familiarity with this
notion of acceptation comes mostly from
reading stuart kaufman
yeah yep yep totally and the exploration
of the adjacent possible and
yeah yep um
the last big whitehead conference i went
to uh
kaufman and um terence deacon were at
the table
when i was presenting on the paper on
whitehead's view of the evolution of
religion and uh the two of them got into
an interesting argument after
i was supposed to be getting questions
but they were arguing instead
but um so yeah i love that that
perspective
and um i think one of the ways that i
would look at this is to say that
you know human human beings um as
the evolution of religion unfolded
through
these phases of initially um just like
ritual um you know dancing and singing
around a fire
gradually taking on the forms uh forms
of myth and
and narrative uh and and symbol
um that get elaborated in in fascinating
ways and
for most of our species history this was
done in a kind of tribalized context
um there weren't any universal religions
until the axial age
right you start to get a more
theoretical elaboration upon
the ritual practice and symbolic
collaboration yeah and the
narrative around the the rituals and
then
it's as if it's one way that i like to
imagine this whole process is like
it's as if the this like human
consciousness is being um
sort of sheltered and grown within an
increasingly
elaborate and thick shell and like it
climaxes in
in i mean all over the world but to use
the you know
example of in like um the christian and
islamic and judaic traditions like these
monumental temple structures and
cathedrals and
i mean there were temples before that
too but it's almost like we're growing a
shell around ourselves and
at some point in modern europe we sort
of
our consciousness got big enough to
break out of that shell
and we all of our development
cognitively
and ethically to the point where
modern science was born was was
sheltered by this religious context
yes um but then what that religious
context gave birth to
broke from the shell and now we're like
naked without any of the ritual symbolic
uh narrative context that gave birth to
us
and we have some surrogate
um sheltering that technology affords
and communication media now have
completely
almost re-encapsulated us within a new
kind of shell
that's not rooted in like virtue or
deliberate
contemplative practice or anything like
that
it's rooted in consumer capitalism but
um
we we can't avoid the way that this this
this shell grows around our
consciousness to shape the way the
values of our society and
and and gives us a a sense of
orientation amidst
the cosmogenesis you know that we emerge
from
and i feel like you know like your work
is an attempt to say well wait a minute
like
we need to re-engage with some of those
wisdom traditions
in the context of our modern scientific
knowledge and technological capacity
and if we can bring these two together
and integrate
um the insight of modern science the
power of modern technology with the
wisdom
of these these traditions and there's
there's a whole
global monopoly of options um
that are intimately there's a there's an
evolutionary process that ties all the
religions together i would say
i'm not a perennialist in the sense that
i think there's one original revelation
and all the religions are like
different paths up the mountain i take
jorge's perspective jorge ferreira's
perspective on
rather than the mountain with many paths
it's
an ocean with many shores yeah yeah yeah
um
but yeah so uh that's kind of how i see
it it's like we
we can't avoid building this like this
shell around ourselves to to give us a
sense of orientation
and protection from an otherwise chaotic
world
and religion used to serve that function
and we need to um
find a way of becoming reverential again
in a in a scientific
context in the midst of an evolutionary
and evolving universe yeah that's very
well said
very well said man that's very well said
thanks that was very good well
i this this seems like a nice place to
close but we're not finished i mean i
would like it
i'm inviting you to further discussion
with me
um i'd i'd i'd like to continue uh you
know doing some voices with raviki with
you
and uh i i was serious about it'd be
great if you you know you and i and evan
had a conversation yeah i foreign had a
conversation i would love i would like
all of that
well that sounds great to me i'm glad to
i'd be glad to come back and chat with
you i uh how about this all email
jorge and you can reach out to evan and
we'll see if we can arrange those two
right
try logs so let's do this as our order
of operations let's you and i have one
more one-on-one
because i feel like we're just ending
for time reasons here i'd like to i'd
like to there's a lot more in your
thinking i'd like to unpack and explore
uh because i i feel like of the video i
i've maybe touched on one or two of the
points that i wanted to talk about
um yeah and i want to read more of your
work
um you sent me i think one paper but
maybe sending me
that one that provoked all the
controversy uh between kaufman and
deacon that would be
i'd like that'd be great i'd like to
read a bit more of your work
so what i'll reach out to evan you reach
out to jorge
uh but let's also set up a time when you
and i can do
another one um i'll get more deeply into
your work
um and then we can unpack it a bit more
because i found what we did today very
rich i hope you did too
yes i did yes i i think for one
avenue here's a proposal one thing i'd
like to talk to you about
because i mentioned it earlier but i
think this this this whitehead in model
you know where the the the the the the
two are folding into each other
in that creativity and and the polarity
of it
i i think that's very consonant with a
dialogical model of reason and i'd like
to explore
because that would be a way of getting
you know a deeper conformity between
um you know the reinvention of
rationality and the reinvention
of reality um and i think that
you know and and the model that again i
have in mind is erigina's model about
the dialectic isn't only a way of
unfolding
you know human rationality it is
actually sort of the grammar
uh of of of god and of reality
um so i'd like to explore that with you
if you if you think if you think that's
an interesting proposal
that sounds great i'll i'll uh i'll go
back and reread my irigina because it's
been a while and
that'll be fun right and so and then
hopefully after that
uh you know you and i and evan and you
and i and jorge could beat it
that we'd have a nice little sort of
series on this right now so
i want to thank you i i really oh well i
i really enjoyed i i already like when i
met you when we were
co-supervising uh well i wasn't a
supervisor but you know i was in the
area committee or whatever i was
um but yeah um
i already like
your presence i i you have a way
trying to make this very clear you have
a way of being present that is gentle
without being flimsy or being sort of
soft um and i find that commendable
there's a richness there's a resiliency
but there's no
there's there's no sort of ruthless
self-promotion or
i just i i given what we've talked about
earlier i think it's
important to recognize uh epistemic
virtue
and point it out and i think you're
exemplifying it in a wonderful way
so in addition to the really rich
content
of the discussion your manner of
presentation is also something
i think that's exemplary and i wanted to
call that out and thank you for that
oh thank you i appreciate that very much
john that's very meaningful to hear
um and uh you know i've had great
teachers
so yeah it shows it really
virtue ethics requires uh
that you have people you can model
yourself on
yeah in relationship too so yeah
great well thank you so much um and i i
very much look forward to our next
dialogue me too thank you so much matt